Guide to the Baldwin-Lima-Hamilton Corporation Records, 1854-1925 M0015
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Baldwin-Lima-Hamilton Corporation records,
1854-1925
M0015
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
5.5 Linear feet
Baldwin Locomotive Works
SCOPE AND CONTENTS
This collection represents a small portion of the records of the Philadelphia steam locomotive production firm known as the Baldwin Locomotive Works until its merger with Lima-Hamilton Corporation. The materials include ledgers, specification books, and drawings for construction and decoration of locomotives, as well as publications of the company. One book deals with the railroads of South America. The collection also includes 436 copy slides (done in 1985) of paint books numbers 1 and 2.
HISTORICAL NOTE
Baldwin Locomotive Works, a Philadelphia steam locomotive production firm founded in 1831, eventually merged with the Lima-Hamilton Corporation and became the Baldwin-Lima-Hamilton Corporation.
Provenance:
Gift of E. Morton Grosser, 1960. The copy slides are a gift of the California State Railway Museum, 1987.
Access Restrictions:
None.
- 75 drawings and plans for locomotive construction, ca. 1887-1918.
  - [Unidentified], 211
  - Locomotive for 2'6" gauge passenger freight service, 591
  - Passenger locomotive, 1125
  - Passenger locomotive, heavy, 1367
  - Passenger locomotive, light, 1368
  - Passenger locomotive, light, "Oosthoek" Rwy., Iowa, 1761
  - Consolidation locomotive, 1978
  - [Unidentified], 2185
  - Ten-wheel locomotive, 1889 June 17; 2196
  - Double trunk four cylinder logging locomotive, 2301
  - Mogul locomotive, 2470
  - Erecting #2484-6, 1892 Dec. 27; 3180
  - Prelim. narrow gauge freight locomotive, 3754
  - Mining locomotive, 100 hp, 4 coupled wheels, 4043
  - Compressed air locomotive, 4-11C146 Ashland Coal & Iron Co., 4432
  - Motor passenger car, 1897 Aug. 6; 4985
  - [Unidentified], 5036
  - Inspection car, 1897 Sept. 15; 5048
  - Double ender passgr. tank loc. for Tsarkoe-Selo Rwy., 5063
  - [Unidentified], 1897 Nov. 3; 5164
  - Tender for Western Rwy. Havana, 5203
  - Inspection car, 1897 Nov. 30; 5218
  - Motor passenger car, 1898 Feb. 11; 5365
  - [Used with #5357], 5385
  - Inspection locomotive, 5483
  - Steam motor car, 5588
  - [Unidentified], 1898 Jan. 8; 5849
  - Fast passenger locomotive, Gt. Northern Rwy. 10-20-1-C-38-4, 6619
  - Compressed air locomotive for German navy station, 1901 Mar. 18; 7378
  - Six coupled locomotive, 7476
  - Compound mogul locomotive Indian State Railway, 1901 May 11; 7490
  - Vanderbilt tender, 1901 May 23; 7526
  - Tank locomotive, Soc. Miniere et Mett. de Penarroya, 1901 May 29; 7548
  - Tender 10-28-E-52,53, 1901 Aug. 1; 7695
  - Prop. arrangement of electric loc. for Miami & Erie Canal Tr. Co., 8015
  - Switching locomotive, 1901 Dec. 18; 8019
  - Passenger locomotive 8-30C Southern Rwy. Based by SK 8-34C DWG#4/8-34C CWG#6 F, 1901 Dec. 20; 8027
  - Tender for oil-burning locomotive, 1902 Apr. 22; 8356
  - Tender for oil-burning locomotive, 1902 Apr. 30; 8375
  - [Unidentified], 8408
  - Ten wheel locomotive, 8766 changed to have fire box 60" wide, not 66", 1902 Oct. 2; 8766A
  - [Unidentified], 9027
  - Fast passenger locomotive "Atlantic" type, NY, NH & Hartford 10-32 1/4C, 1903 Jan. 29; 9047
  - Ten wheel locomotive, 1903 Feb. 9; 9068
  - Four wheel tender for "Old Ironsides,", 1903 Jan.; 9079
  - Ten wheel locomotive, 1903 Mar. 5; 9151
  - Double end locomotive, 1903 May 9; 9345
  - Double end locomotive, 10-18 1/4 D, 1903 May 27; 9422
  - Consolidation locomotive, 1903 July 9; 9541
  - Tender 7,000 gallon capacity, 9602
  - [Unidentified], 1904 Jan. 12; 10020
  - Switching engine, 1904 June 1; 10487
  - Balanced 10 wheel locomotive, 10 26/48 DD NC & St. C., 1905 May 9; 11394
  - Consolidation locomotive, 1905 Aug. 15; 11694
  - Mallet compound locomotive, 12 26.38 DD Chilean State Rwy., 1905 Nov. 1; 11958
  - Ten wheeled locomotive 10-36D, 1905 Nov. 24; 12038
  - Balanced compound loc. heating surface, 1905 Dec. 16; 12101
  - Balanced Atlantic type loc. 10 27/47 1/4C, 1906 Jan. 2; 12141
  - Balanced compound ten wheel locomotive 10 27/48 D, 1906 Jan 2; 12142,3,4
  - Balanced compound ten wheel loc. Italian State Rwy., 1906 Jan. 17; 12185
  - Consolidation locomotive, 1906 Jan. 22; 12205
  - Pacific type loc. 12-38 1/4D, 1906 Jan. 30; 12238
  - Ten wheel loc. 10-36 D, 1906 Mar. 16; 12359
  - Balanced compound Pacific type locomotive 12 28/48, 1906 Apr. 6; 12442
  - 12-28 1/4 D Central Norte, 1906 May 31; 12607
  - Switching loc. CRR of NJ heating surface, 12666
  - Outline of Consolidation loc. as planned for Western Pac. Rwy., 1906 Aug. 7; 12818
  - Switching locomotive, 1906 Aug. 23; 12863
  - Switching locomotive 6-32-D, 12871
  - Outline of tender - Wstn. Pac. Ry., 1906 Aug. 28; 12878
  - Consolidation loc. 10-36E Maine Central, 1907 Mar. 9; 13453
  - Consolidation loc. 10-36E W. R. Grace, 1907 Apr. 19; 13572
  - Wheelspacing/loads of heavy passenger loc. 1870-1908, 1909 Feb. 24; 15734
  - Wheelspacing/loads of heavy freight loc. 1870-1908, 1909 Feb. 24; 15735
  - 100 Hp. Boiler for 125 lbs. pressure Tees, 1912 June 24; 21845
  - Double end tank locomotive, 1915 Feb. 3; 27889
  - Gas engine starting motor assembly, 1918 July 25; 37221
- Disbound ledger: Detail Finish Work (Box 3a)
- Six erecting cards (plans for the building of locomotives), ca. 1879 (Box 3a)
  - 1. Cylinder #1008
  - 2. Boiler #374
  - 3. Grate #856
  - 4. E. C. #142
  - 5. E. C. #215
  - 6. E. C. #448
- Single color plate, drawn by J. Ord (Box 3a)
- Disbound ledger: Engine Drawings (types of locomotive), with blue line drawings (Box 3b)
  General note
  Microfilm of this ledger is available.
- Ledger: Engine Specifications, 1864-1869 (Box 4)
- Ledger: Card Directory (key to plans and drawings) (Box 5)
- Ledger: painting samples for railway cars (Box 6)
- Ledger: painting samples for railway cars (Box 7)
- Ledger: Boiler bills, 1884-1885 (Box 8)
- Ledger: Specificatons and regulations concerning production (Box 8)
- Ledger: Roads and numbers of engines built by BLW (Box 8)
- Ledger: Driving and truck wheels, 1860-1862 (Box 8)
- Ledger: Patent royalties, 1889-1890 (Box 8)
- Atlantic steam packet chart, by James Wyle (map of Atlantic Ocean, n.d.) (Box 8)
- Booklet: Locomotive Data, published by BLW, 1920 (Box 8)
- Book: The Baldwin Locomotive Works - Catalog of Locomotives (reprint of 1915 Rand, McNally & Co. book) (Box 8)
- Book: The Locomotives that Baldwin Built, by Fred Westing, 1966 (Box 8)
- Ledger: Law and general information. Drawing room. (Box 8)
- Ledger: Pattern directory, 1854-1877 (Box 9)
- Ledger: Railroads of South America, 1894-1898 (Box 10)
- Copy slides (436) of paint books 1 and 2, 1985 (Box 11)